Guide to the Académie française autograph collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Académie française autograph collection
1637-1926
1750-1900
GEN MSS 1339
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes)
Correspondence and other documents signed by circa 200 members of the Académie française, 1637-1926 and undated, assembled by an unidentified collector, possibly American autograph collector Howes Norris, Jr. (1867-1938), of Vineyard Haven, Massachusetts. Most are autograph letters, signed; other contents include literary writings, legal documents, and a few documents concerning administration of the Académie française. Many are accompanied by descriptions from vendor catalogs, engraved portraits, clippings, or notes of former owners. Correspondence includes an autograph letter, signed, from Alexis de Tocqueville to Robert Walsh, consul general of the United States in Paris, 1845 June 10.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop on an unknown fund, 1954.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Académie française
Learned society for the French language, founded in 1635 by Richelieu.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence and other documents signed by circa 200 members of the Académie française, 1637-1926 and undated, assembled by an unidentified collector, possibly American autograph collector Howes Norris, Jr. (1867-1938), of Vineyard Haven, Massachusetts. Most are autograph letters, signed; other contents include literary writings, legal documents, and a few documents concerning administration of the Académie française. Many are accompanied by descriptions from vendor catalogs, engraved portraits, clippings, or notes of former owners. Correspondence includes an autograph letter, signed, from Alexis de Tocqueville to Robert Walsh, consul general of the United States in Paris, 1845 June 10. Documents relating to Maurice Donnay and Albert, comte de Mun, include signatures on printed cards identified as "The autograph collection of Howes Norris, Jr."
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by name.
Learned institutions and societies -- France; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; France -- Politics and government; France -- Intellectual life; Engravings (prints); Norris, Howes, 1867-1938; Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859; Académie française
- Achard, Amédée, 1814-1875, [1867?] September 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Adam, Paul, 1862-1920, 1899 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Aignan, M. (Etienne), 1773-1824, [1803 September 26] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Albert de Luynes, Paul d', 1703-1788, 1776 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Ampère, J.-J. (Jean Jacques), 1800-1864, [1828] August 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ancelot, M. (François), 1794-1854, no year October 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Andrieux, F.-G.-J.-S. (François-Guillaume-Jean-Stanislas), 1759-1833, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Argenson, Marc-Pierre de Voyer, comte d', 1696-1764, 1711 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Arnault, A.-V. (Antoine-Vincent), 1766-1834, 1824 September [3?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Audiffret-Pasquier, Edme Armand Gaston, duc de, 1823-1905, 1881 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Auger, L.-S. (Louis-Simon), 1772-1829, 1812 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Augier, Émile, 1820-1889, 1873 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Aumale, Henri d'Orléans, duc d', 1822-1897., 1897 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Auriol, George, 1863-1938, 1925 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Autran, Joseph Antoine, 1813-1877, [1848 March 9] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Ballanche, Pierre Simon, 1776-1847, no year June 6 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Baour-Lormian, M. (Pierre-Marie-François-Louis), 1770-1854, no year "3 floréal" (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Barante, Amable-Guillaume-Prosper Brugière, baron de, 1782-1866, 1854 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Barboux, Henri-Martin, 1834-1910, 1889 September 4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Bausset, Louis François de, 1748-1824, 1812 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Becquerel, M. (Antoine César), 1788-1878, no year December 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Belle-Isle, Charles Louis Auguste Fouquet, duc de, 1684-1761, 1758 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Benoît, Pierre, 1886-1962, 1921 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Bérard, Léon, 1876-1960, 1897 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Bernard, Claude, 1813-1878, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Bernard, Tristan, 1866-1947, no year February 23 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Bernis, François-Joachim de Pierre de, 1715-1794, 1777 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Bernstein, Henry, 1876-1953, 1908 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Berryer, Pierre-Antoine, 1790-1868, no year September 19 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Bignon, Jean Paul, 1662-1743, 1709 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Biot, Jean-Baptiste, 1774-1862, 1846 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Bisson, Alexandre, 1848-1912, 1911 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Blanc, Charles, 1813-1882, 1872 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Bonald, Louis-Gabriel-Ambroise, vicomte de, 1754-1840, no year March 10 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Bornier, Henri de, vicomte, 1825-1901, no year November 23 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Boufflers, Stanislas-Jean de, 1738-1815, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Bougainville, Jean-Pierre de, 1722-1763, 1749 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Brifaut, Charles, 1781-1857, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Buffon, Georges Louis Leclerc, comte de, 1707-1788, 1763 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Cailhava, Jean François, 1731-1813, no year "27 nivôse" (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Cambacérès, Jean Jacques Régis de, 1753-1824, 1807 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Campenon, M. (François Nicolas Vincent), 1772-1843, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Capus, Alfred, 1858-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Caro, E. (Elme-Marie), 1826-1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Champagny, Franz, comte de, 1804-1882, no year November 13 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Champfleury, 1821-1889, 1882 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Charmes, Francis, 1848-1916, 1913 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Colbert, Jacques-Nicolas, 1655-1707, 1707 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Constant, Benjamin, 1767-1830, no year April 13 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Courteline, Georges, pseud., undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Crécy, Louis Verjus, comte de, 1629-1709, [1680 March 26?] (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Cuvier, Georges, baron, 1769-1832, 1808, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Cuvillier-Fleury, M. (Alfred-Auguste), 1802-1887, 1862 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Dacier, Bon-Joseph, 1742-1833, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Daru, Pierre-Antoine-Noël-Bruno, comte, 1767-1829, 1821 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Dekobra, Maurice, 1885-1973, 1926 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Delavigne, Casimir, 1793-1843, 1835 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Donnay, Maurice, 1859-1945, 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  Scope and Contents
  "The autograph collection of Howes Norris, Jr."
- Dorgelès, Roland, 1886-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Doucet, Camille, 1812-1895, 1875 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Dubois, Guillaume, 1656-1723, 1722 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Duclos, Charles Pinot-, 1704-1772, 1756 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Dufaure, M. (Jules), 1798-1881, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Dupin, M. (André-Marie-Jean-Jacques), 1783-1865, no year April 11 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- Duras, Emmanuel-Céleste-Augustin de Durfort, duc de, 1741-1800, 1770 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Empis, M. (Adolphe Dominique Florent Joseph Simonis), 1795-1868, 1846 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Esménard, J. (Joseph), 1767-1811, 1809 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Estrées, César d', 1628-1714, 1671? (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Estrées, Louis-Charles-César Le Tellier, duc d', 1695-1771, 1716 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- Étienne, Charles-Guillaume, 1777-1845, 1833 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- Falloux du Coudray, Alfred-Frédéric-Pierre, comte de, 1811-1886, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
- Favre, Jules, 1809-1880, 1841 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- Feletz, Charles-Marie, 1767-1850, no year February [20?] (Box 1, Folder 73)
- Ferrand, Antoine-François-Claude, comte, 1751-1825, 1814 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Féval, Paul, 1817-1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Figuier, Louis, 1819-1894, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Fleury, André Hercule de, 1653-1743, 1728 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Flourens, P. (Pierre), 1794-1867, 1839 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- Foncemagne, Étienne Lauréault de, 1694-1779, [1768] March 12 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Fontanes, Louis, marquis de, 1757-1821, 1813 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- François de Neufchâteau, Nicolas Louis, comte, 1750-1828, 1790 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Frayssinous, D. (Denis), 1765-1841, 1819 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Freycinet, Charles de, 1828-1923, 1872 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Garat, Dominique-Joseph, comte, 1749-1833, 1793 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 84)
- Gay, Sophie, 1776-1852, 1848 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Gérard, Rosemonde, 1871-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Ginisty, Paul, 1855-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
- Goncourt, Jules de, 1830-1870, 1859 January 26 (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Gratry, A. (Auguste), 1805-1872, undated (Box 2, Folder 89)
- Gréard, Octave, 1828-1904, 1891 March 24 (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Guillaume, Eugène, 1822-1905, 1875 December 3 (Box 2, Folder 91)
- Guiraud, Alexandre, baron, 1788-1847, 1841 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 92)
- Halévy, Léon, 1802-1883, 1847 September 3 (Box 2, Folder 93)
- Haraucourt, Edmond, 1888 October 22 (Box 2, Folder 94)
- Harcourt, François-Henri, duc d', 1726-1802, undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
- Haussonville, comte d', 1843-1924, 1883 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 96)
- Heredia, José-Maria de, 1842-1905, [1891?] March 29 (Box 2, Folder 97)
- Hermant, Abel, 1862-1950, 1895 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 98)
- Hervé, Edouard, 1872 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 99)
- Houssaye, Arsène, 1815-1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
  Poem
- Janin, Jules, 1804-1874, 1851 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 101)
- Jay, A. (Antoine), 1770-1854, [1820?] December 5 (Box 2, Folder 102)
- Jullian, Camille, 1859-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 103)
- Labiche, Eugène, 1815-1888., 1861 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 104)
- La Cépède, M. le comte de (Bernard Germain Etienne de La Ville sur Illon), 1756-1825, [1804 January 10] (Box 2, Folder 105)
- Lacordaire, Henri-Dominique, 1802-1861, 1833 October 9 (Box 2, Folder 106)
- Lacretelle, Charles, 1766-1855, undated (Box 2, Folder 107)
- Lacretelle, Pierre-Louis de, 1751-1824, no year July 16 (Box 2, Folder 108)
- Lacuée, Jean-Girard, comte de Cessac, 1752-1841, no year "1 brumaire" (Box 2, Folder 109)
- La Force, Henri-Jacques-Nompar de Caumont, duc de, 1675-1726, 1717 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 110)
- La Harpe, Jean-François de, 1739-1803, undated (Box 2, Folder 111)
- Lalande, Joseph Jérôme Le Français de, 1732-1807, 1789 February 23 (Box 2, Folder 112)
- Lally-Tolendal, Trophime-Gérard, marquis de, 1751-1830, undated (Box 2, Folder 113)
- Laprade, Victor de, 1812-1883, 1863 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 114)
- Le Brun, Ponce Denis Ecouchard, 1729-1807, undated (Box 2, Folder 115)
- Lecomte, Georges, 1867-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 116)
- Lecomte, Jules, undated (Box 2, Folder 117)
- Legouvé, Gabriel, 1764-1812, [1809 September] (Box 2, Folder 118)
- Lemercier, Népomucène-Louis, 1771-1840, 1816 May (Box 2, Folder 119)
- Lemoinne, John Marguerite Émile, 1815-1892, undated (Box 2, Folder 120)
- Lemontey, Pierre-Edouard, 1762-1826, 1807 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 121)
- Littré, Émile Maximilien Paul, 1801-1881, 1873 July 31 (Box 2, Folder 122)
- Loyson, Hyacinthe, 1827-1912, 1905 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 123)
- Madelin, Louis, 1871-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 124)
- Maindron, Maurice, 1857-1911, 1909 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 125)
- Maret, Hugues-Bernard, duc de Bassano, 1763-1839, no year June 2 (Box 2, Folder 126)
- Marmier, Xavier, 1809-1892, undated (Box 2, Folder 127)
- Marmontel, Jean-François, 1723-1799, undated (Box 2, Folder 128)
- Martin, Henri, 1810-1883, undated (Box 2, Folder 129)
- Mathieu, cardinal, 1839-1908, undated (Box 2, Folder 130)
- Mazade, Charles de, 1820-1893, no year August 18 (Box 2, Folder 131)
- Meilhac, Henri, 1831-1897, undated (Box 2, Folder 132)
- Merlin, M. (Philippe-Antoine), 1754-1838, [1796 October 19] (Box 2, Folder 133)
- Méry, Joseph, 1798-1865, no year September 30 (Box 2, Folder 134)
- Meurice, Paul, 1820-1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 135)
- Michaud, J. Fr. (Joseph Fr.), 1767-1839, no year October 8 (Box 2, Folder 136)
- Michelet, Jules, 1798-1874, no year [April 4] (Box 2, Folder 137)
- Mignet, M. (François-Auguste-Marie-Alexis), 1796-1884, 1844 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 138)
- Millot, abbé (Claude François Xavier), 1726-1785, 1770 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 139)
- Molé, Louis-Mathieu, comte, 1781-1855, 1849 August 7 (Box 2, Folder 140)
- Monselet, Charles, 1825-1888, undated (Box 2, Folder 141)
- Mun, Albert, comte de, 1841-1914, 1878, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  "The autograph collection of Howes Norris, Jr." Includes photograph of Mun
- Nisard, D. (Désiré), 1806-1888, 1856 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 143)
- Noailles, Paul, duc de, 1802-1885, 1842 October 31 (Box 2, Folder 144)
- Olivet, Pierre-Joseph Thoulier, 1682-1768, undated (Box 2, Folder 145)
- O'Rell, Max, 1848-1903, 1892 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 146)
- Pasquier, Étienne-Denis, duc, 1767-1862, undated (Box 2, Folder 147)
- Pastoret, Claude Emmanuel Joseph Pierre, marquis de, 1755-1840, no year October 6 (Box 2, Folder 148)
- Patin, M. (Henri), 1793-1876, 1860 November 19 (Box 2, Folder 149)
- Péréfixe de Beaumont, Hardouin de, 1605-, 1668 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 150)
- Perraud, Adolphe, 1900 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 151)
- Picard, L.-B. (Louis-Benoît), 1769-1828, no year "24 floréal" (Box 2, Folder 152)
- Pichon, Stephen, 1857-1933, 1903 September 16 (Box 2, Folder 153)
- Polignac, Melchior de, 1661-1742?, 1720 September (Box 2, Folder 154)
- Ponsard, François, 1814-1867, undated (Box 2, Folder 155)
- Portalis, Jean-Etienne-Marie, 1746-1807, [1805 May 25] (Box 2, Folder 156)
- Potier de Novion, Nicolas, 1618-1693, 1690 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 157)
- Prévost-Paradol, Lucien Anatole, 1829-1870, undated (Box 2, Folder 158)
- Quélen, Hyacinthe-Louis de, 1778-1839, 1838 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 159)
- Quinet, Edgar, 1803-1875, 1832 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 160)
- Radonvilliers, Claude François Lizarde de, 1710-1789, 1773 February 20 (Box 2, Folder 161)
- Raynouard, M. (François-Just-Marie), 1761-1836, 1817 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 162)
- Regnaud de Saint-Jean-d'Angély, Michel-Louis-Etienne, comte, 1762-1819, [1798 November 6] (Box 2, Folder 163)
- Régnier-Desmarais, abbé (François-Séraphin), 1632-1713, 1702 September 22 (Box 2, Folder 164)
- Rémusat, Charles de, 1797-1875, no year July 8 (Box 2, Folder 165)
- Renard, Jules, 1864-1910, no year January 4 (Box 2, Folder 166)
- Richelieu, Louis François Armand du Plessis, duc de, 1696-1788, 1766 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 167)
- Roederer, P.-L. (Pierre-Louis), 1754-1835, 1812 August 4 (Box 2, Folder 168)
- Roger, Barthélemy Joseph Fulcran, 1767-1841, no year September 23 (Box 2, Folder 169)
- Rohan, Armand Gaston Maximilien de, 1674-1749, 1730 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 170)
- Rothelin, Charles d'Orléans de, 1691-1744, 1731 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 171)
  Appended to letter from Louis de Pardaillan de Gondrin, 1731 February 23
- Roujon, Henry, 1853-1914, 1890 January 7 (Box 2, Folder 172)
- Rousse, Edmond, 1817-1906, 1893 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 173)
- Royer-Collard, Pierre-Paul, 1763-1845, 1817 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 174)
- Sacy, Samuel S. de (Samuel Silvestre), 1873 February 26 (Box 3, Folder 175)
- Saint-Aignan, François Honorat de Beauvilliers, 1607-1687, 1674 October 4 (Box 3, Folder 176)
- Saint-Ange, Ange-François Fariau de, 1747-1810, no year November 19 (Box 3, Folder 177)
- Saint-Marc Girardin, 1801-1873., undated (Box 3, Folder 178)
- Saint-Priest, Alexis Guignard de, comte, 1805-1851., undated (Box 3, Folder 179)
- Sainte-Aulaire, comte de (Louis Clair de Beaupoil), 1778-1854, no year May 3 (Box 3, Folder 180)
- Salvandy, N.-A. de (Narcisse-Achille), 1795-1856., 1853 March 16 (Box 3, Folder 181)
- Sandeau, Jules, 1811-1883, undated (Box 3, Folder 182)
- Say, Jean Baptiste, 1767-1832, undated (Box 3, Folder 183)
- Say, Léon, 1826-1896, undated (Box 3, Folder 184)
- Sedaine, 1719-1797, 1766 April 8 (Box 3, Folder 185)
- Séguier, Pierre, 1588-1672, 1637 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 186)
- Ségur, Louis-Philippe, comte de, 1753-1830, 1816 December 25 (Box 3, Folder 187)
- Ségur, Philippe-Paul, comte de, 1780-1873, 1844 June 3 (Box 3, Folder 188)
- Sicard, Roch Ambroise, 1742-1822, 1809 October 13 (Box 3, Folder 189)
- Sorel, Albert, 1842-1906, 1891 October 15 (Box 3, Folder 190)
- Soumet, Alexandre, 1788-1845, undated (Box 3, Folder 191)
- Suard, J. B. A. (Jean Baptiste Antoine), 1734-1817, no year "12 messidor" (Box 3, Folder 192)
- Tharaud, Jean, 1877-1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 193)
- Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1805-1859, 1845 June 10 (Box 3, Folder 194)
  Autograph letter, signed, to Robert Walsh, consul general of the United States in Paris
- Vatout, Jean, undated (Box 3, Folder 195)
- Vicq-d'Azyr, M. (Félix), 1748-1794, 1791 September (Box 3, Folder 196)
- Viel-Castel, Louis de, 1800-1887, undated (Box 3, Folder 197)
- Viennet, Jean-Pons-Guillaume, 1777-1868, 1841 March 30 (Box 3, Folder 198)
- Villars, Honoré-Armand, 1702-1770, 1761 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 199)
- Vitet, Louis, 1802-1873, 1845 September 23 (Box 3, Folder 200)
- Vogüé, Eugène-Melchior, vicomte de, 1848-1910, 1880 February 16 (Box 3, Folder 201)
- Volney, C.-F. (Constantin-François), 1757-1820, 1815 August 28 (Box 3, Folder 202)
- Watelet, Claude-Henri, 1718-1786, 1779 December 30 (Box 3, Folder 203)
- Willy, 1859-1931, [1893] (Box 3, Folder 204)